-= THE LAST FANTASY 荣誉出品 =-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业途径
-= TLF字幕组 =-
翻译/校对｜gentalpass
特别鸣谢｜PF_coldbench
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
潜水钟与蝴蝶
- 看！他醒了  - 通知科奇东医生，快！
- Look! He's waking.  - Page Dr. Cocheton. Quickly.
科奇东医生请到一一九病房
Dr. Cocheton to room 119, please.
波比先生，睁开眼，请睁开眼睛
Mr. Bauby, open your eyes. Open your eyes.
波比先生，把眼睛睁开
Mr. Bauby, open your eyes.
你已经睡了很久了，现在终于醒过来了，能听到我吗？
You've been asleep for a long time, you're waking up now. Can you hear me?
[是的，我能听到]
[Yes, I'm hearing you.]
[发生了什么？]
[What's happening?]
[天啊，医院]
[Jesus, a hospital.]
波比先生，请把眼睛睁大
Mr. Bauby, open your eyes wide.
尽量把眼睛睁开
Try to keep them open.
对，就这样，眼睛盯着我手里的灯
Yes, like that. Follow this lamp with your eyes.
好的
Alright.
别怕，你现在在医院
Don't be alarmed. You're in a hospital.
我是科奇东医生，他们是护士
I'm a doctor. My name's Cocheton. These are nurses.
我们会好好照顾你的
We're here to take care of you.
还记得都发生了什么吗？
Do you remember what happened?
还记得发生的事情吗？
[只有一些模糊的片段]
[Just vague images]
你现在在加来贝克海滨的海军医院
You're in the Naval Hospital, Berck-sur-Mer. On the coast. At Calais.
先前你在巴黎接受治疗，之后转院到这里
You were treated first in Paris, and then brought here.
这些你都记得吗？
Do you remember that?
吉恩-多米尼克
Jean-Dominique.
你中风了
You've had a stroke.
昏迷了近三个礼拜
You've been in a coma for almost three weeks.
不过现在你醒过来了，一切都会好起来的
But now you're waking up and you'll be fine.
我保证
I promise you.
[谢谢]
[Thank you]
我得给你做些简单测试
I have to give you some simple tests.
眼睛看着我
Keep your eyes on me.
很好
Good.
眼睛跟着我的手指走，好的
Follow my finger. Good.
我说“眨眼”，你就眨眼
When I say blink, please blink.
好极了
Excellent.
好，现在告诉我你的名字
Now, tell me your name.
[吉恩-多米尼克·波比]
[Jean-Dominique Bauby.]
来，努力试下
Come on, try
[我刚不是告诉你了吗]
[I just did.]
努力试下，说出你的名字
Try really hard, say your name.
[吉恩-多米尼克·波比]
[Jean-Dominique Bauby.]
试试说下你孩子的名字
Try saying your children's names.
[西奥菲勒，席莱斯特，霍顿斯]
[Theophile, Celeste, Hortense.]
别着急
Don't worry.
虽然缓慢，但你的语言功能会恢复的
It's a slow process. But your speech will come back.
[什么？难道你听不到我？医生？医生？]
[What? Can't you hear me, doctor? Doctor?]
[到底是怎么了？我说不了话了]
[What's happening? I can't speak.]
[他们听不到我说话，天啊]
[They can't hear me. Oh my God.]
[我说不了话了]
[I can't speak.]
[我到底是怎么了？]
[What's happened to me?]
[我叫吉恩-多米尼克·波比]
[My name is Jean-Dominique Bauby.]
[医生？]
[Doctor?]
[好吧，好吧]
[All right, all right.]
[我中了风，我的语言和记忆都会恢复的]
[I've had a stroke my speech'll come back my memory will come back]
一切都会好起来的，波比先生，我们会好好照顾你的
Everything will be alright, Mr. Bauby. We are here to care for you.
[我会耐心的]
[I'll be patient.]
[好的]
[OK.]
[好的，我相信你们]
[OK, I believe you.]
[这些花是谁送来的？]
[Who brought these flowers?]
[玫瑰花]
[Roses.]
[伊莱斯]
[Elese]
睡得还好吗？
Did you sleep well?
让我来看看
Let's see.
你的神经治疗师莱裴奇医生要来查房
You're going to have an important visitor. Dr. Lepage, your neurologist.
所以希望你好好表现
So we want you at your very best.
早上好
Good morning.
我是神经治疗师，亚伦·莱裴奇医生，相信你已经见过科奇东医生了
I'm Alain Lepage, your neurologist. You know Dr. Cocheton, of course.
吉恩-多米尼克…不，你的朋友都叫你吉多
Jean-Dominique... no, no, your friends call you Jean-Do.
我也会这么称呼你，把我当作你的朋友
So that's what I'm going to call you. Think of me as your friend.
[没问题，医生]
[Sure Doctor.]
作为朋友，我明白眼下对你来说有多困难
As a friend I know how difficult this is for you.
没有人向你说明你的病情
Nobody here has explained to you the full extent of your condition.
你的情况，医学界称之为脑血管意外
You've had what we call a cerebrovascular accident.
就是令你的脑干无法正常工作
It's put your brain stem out of action.
脑干的作用非常重要
The brain stem is an essential component of our internal computer
它是连接大脑和脊髓的桥梁
the link between the brain and the spinal cord.
要在过去，我们会称你这种情况为严重中风
In the past, we would have said you'd had a massive stroke.
生还几率近乎为零
You would very probably have died.
但是现在医学发达
But now we have such improved resuscitation techniques
我们可以延长生命
that we're able to prolong life.
[你就管这叫生命？]
[Is this life?]
[- 这就叫生命？ - 对，延长生命]
[- Is this life?  - Yes, prolong life.]
我不会对你隐瞒病情，吉多，你现在全身瘫痪
I'm not going to mince words, Jean-Do. You are completely paralyzed.
你已经意识到了自己不能讲话
You have realised you are unable to speak.
我们管这个叫…
You have what we call...
…闭锁综合症
...'locked-in syndrome'.
[闭锁综合症]
[locked-in syndrome.]
闭锁综合症
Locked-in syndrome.
这必将给你带来诸多不便，但是你的情况十分罕见
It will be of no comfort to you but your condition is extremely rare.
我们对你的病因还毫无头绪
And we simply don't know the cause.
你不吸烟，也不酗酒
You don't smoke and you're not a heavy drinker.
这一切都是突如其来
It just happened all of a sudden.
但是，尽管全身瘫痪…
However, apart from being totally paralysed...
…你的其他方面都很正常
...you are normal in every other respect.
[正常？]
[Normal?]
还有希望
There is hope.
你的大脑清醒正常
Your brain is functioning.
你能明白我们，你的眼睛随我们的运动而移动
You're able to understand us. You follow our movements with your eyes.
尽管对你的右眼我有些失望
Although I'm not entirely happy with your right eye.
这部分肌肉坏死，看到没？
This muscle doesn't work, see?
眼球缺少水分
The eye doesn't get moisturized.
恐怕我们要把它遮起来
I'm afraid we have to cover that.
是不是？
Don't we?
[遮起来？]
[Cover?]
[他想遮什么？]
[What does he want to cover?]
但是我会想办法补救的
but I'll take a second guess on that.
我们希望你好好休息几天
We want you to take it easy for a few days.
[难道我现在不是在休息吗？]
[What d'you think I'm doing now?]
…之后两个美女会来看你
...and then two beautiful young women will visit you.
可是真正的美女啊
And when I say beautiful, I mean beautiful.
[好]
[Fine.]
他们两个棒极了，了不起的治疗师，有妙手回春的本事
They are great. Outstanding therapists and miracle workers.
[别说什么奇迹]
[No miracles please.]
就像我刚说的，还有希望…
And so, as I say, there's hope..
[你刚才的那些就叫希望？]
[That's what you all showed me.]
我们会好好照顾你的，吉多
You'll be well looked after, Jean-Do. Really.
[这话说的好]
[That's a good start.]
我们会好好照顾你的
You'll be well looked after.
早上好
Good morning.
[难道这是在天堂？]
[Have I gone to heaven?]
我叫亨瑞特
I'm Henrite.
- 我是玛丽  - 你可以眨眼，对吗？
- And I'm Marie.  - You can blink your eyes, don't you?
你眨一下眼就是“是”的意思，眨两下眼就是“不是”
So, I want you to blink once for yes, twice for no.
[太好了！两个大美人，而我却是不可救药]
[Fine! Two beauties and I'm helpless.]
你能读这个吗？
Can you read that?
[什么？]
[Where?]
- 杜兰德，语言障碍科  - 你能看到“杜兰德”吗？
- H. Durand, logopediste.  - Can you see Durand?
[- 好的，波比先生  - 你是否还是单身？]
[- Good, Mr. Bauby.  - Mrs. or Miss?]
我是你的理疗师，首先你得学会吞咽食物
I'm your physical therapist. First you have to learn again to swallow.
所以我会先帮你在舌头和嘴唇上做些练习
So I'll be working on your tongue and lips.
[听起来还挺有意思]
[Sounds fun.]
我是你的语言训练师
And I'm your speech therapist.
在你开口讲话之前，我会想办法叫你和外界交流的
Until you can actually speak again I have to find a way for you to communicate.
你的病情非常罕见
Your condition is extremely rare.
[我知道]
[I know.]
- …所以我们会尽最大努力帮助你  - 那我们现在就开始吧
- ...we're going to have to work very hard.  - So we'd better get started.
没错，我只是过来自我介绍一下的，再见
Exactly. I just came in to introduce myself. See you.
[再见]
[See you.]
我想叫你知道…
I want you to know...
…这大概是我所接受的最重要的工作
...that this is perhaps the most important job I've ever been given.
我势在必得，当然还需要你的帮助支持
and I'm determined to succeed. With your help, of course.
我需要问你几个问题，希望你能理解
I think you understand, but I will ask you some questions.
好吗？
OK?
记住，眨一下眼睛代表“同意”
Remember, you answer by blinking once for yes
两下就表示“反对”
or twice for no..
我是男人吗？
Am I a man?
是女人吗？
Am I a woman?
是不是阳光太刺眼了？
Is the sun too bright for you?
现在是午夜时分吗？
Is it midnight now?
[这都是些什么问题啊？]
[What kinds of questions are this?]
我们现在是在巴黎吗？
Are we in Paris?
那是在贝克吗？
Are we in Berck?
木头能漂浮吗？
Does wood float?
[应该不能吧]
[I don't think so.]
你还记得中风的事吗？
Do you remember having your stroke?
你是《世界时装之苑》杂志主编吗？
Were you the editor of Elle magazine?
[是的，我是《世界时装之苑》的总编]
[Yes, I was the editor-in-chief of Elle.]
到阿勒亚去
To Alyā.
你的右眼功能失常
Your right eye isn't working properly.
能听到我吗？
Can you hear me?
你的右眼功能失常，所以我要把它缝起来
Your right eye isn't working properly. I'm going to sew it up.
[缝起来？]
[Sew it up?]
这是因为…
That happens...
…角膜溃烂的原因
...an ulcerated cornea.
我总是去圣莫丽斯滑雪，现在是滑雪的最佳季节
I've been skiing in St. Moritz. It's wonderful there now.
[这个我TMD才不关心]
[I don't give a shit.]
迎风滑下雪坡的感觉真是太爽了
nothing like sailing down a slope with the wind in your face..
[离我远点]
[Keep away from me]
别担心
Don't worry
[滚开]
[keep away from me]
一点都不痛
You won't feel a thing.
[别这样]
[Please.]
[不，请别这样…]
[No, please don't...]
一点都不会痛，别动
You won't feel anything. Just be quiet.
[不要]
[Don't]
这种小手术我做的多了去了
I've done this dozens of times.
没事的
It will be fine.
别怕
Don't worry.
再缝几针，马上就好了
Almost done. A few more pinpricks.
好极了，真是太好了
Perfect, even if I say so myself.
缝好了
Done.
我们要给你打扮一番，叫你高兴高兴
We're going to dress you to cheer you up a bit.
之后有个意外的惊喜给你
Afterwards we have a surprise.
让你试下这个轮椅
We're going to try you in this wheelchair.
好的
OK.
推他几下，好吗？
Wheel him up and down, will you?
这些都是我的学生，别在意他们
These are my students. Pay no attention to them.
我想确定他那样坐，不会引起肌肉痉挛
I want to be sure that sitting like that won't trigger uncontrollable muscular spasms.
给他的头部加一个靠垫
He needs a cushion behind his head
对不起，吉多，我们必须这么做，好，好极了
Sorry we have to do this to you, Jean-Do. Excellent. Excellent.
你用这轮椅应该没问题
You can handle the wheelchair.
[你能坐这轮椅～真给我面子啊]
[You can handle the wheelchair. What an honor.]
这是叫你高兴一下的好消息
That is good news.
现在是给你的意外惊喜
And now for the surprise
[哦，天啊，那是谁？是我吗？]
[Oh my God, who's that? Me?]
[我看上去就好像刚从防腐剂液里捞出来一样]
[I look as if I've emerged from a vat of formaldehyde.]
[太可怕了]
[Horrible.]
[这就是给我的意外惊喜吗？就是见识下自己现在的尊容？]
[Is that my surprise? To see myself?]
[席琳]
[Cine.]
你好吗？来，我来给你说明一些情况
How are you? OK, let me explain that.
是不是个意外惊喜，吉多？你妻子第一个来探望你
Isn't this a wonderful surprise, Jean-Do? Your first visitor is your wife.
[不，她只是我孩子的母亲]
[No, she's the mother of my children.]
他什么都能理解
He understands everything. Everything.
如果有话问他，最好是“是”或“不是”的问题，好吗？
If you ask a question, make it a yes-or-no question. OK?
他会眨眼，眨一下是肯定，两下是否定
He'll blink. One for yes, two for no.
好的
OK.
还有一点，说话的时候最好正对着他
One more thing. Stay in front of him when you talk to him. OK?
要是站在这里，或者这里，他就看不到你了
If you stand here, he can't see you, and here neither.
像这样的和他交谈，是不是，吉多？
Talk to him like this. Right, Jean-Do?
你们单独待会儿吧，你们一定有很多话要谈…
I'll leave you. I'm sure you have a lot to say to each other...
他们告诉我，你…
They tell me you're doing...
大家都要我问候祝福你
Everyone sends their love. And their prayers.
我没有带孩子们来
I didn't bring the children.
我觉得应该先来看看你
I thought I should see you first.
他们都很好，而且很想念你
They're both well. They miss you.
席莱斯特每晚都为你祈祷
Celeste prays for you every night.
你想见他们吗？
Do you want me to bring them?
你不想见见他们？
Don't you want to see them?
劳伦想来看你，你想见他吗？
Laurent wants to visit. Do you want to see him?
你想见他
Him you want to see.
我会告诉他的
I'll tell him.
她来看过你吗？
Has she been to see you?
我见过你的语言治疗师，我很喜欢她
I've met the speech therapist. I like her.
她觉得她可以帮助你
She thinks she can help you.
别哭
Please don't cry.
[我知道贝克车站，能预见她此时的心情]
[I know Berck station. I can see her now.]
[那里是世界上最伤感之地]
[It's the most depressing place in the world.]
[至少对于小时候在那里度假的我来说是伤感之地]
[Well, it certainly was when I had my holidays here as a child.]
[贝克，暑假终结点]
[Berck. The end of summer.]
[和老爸一起默默地等待驶往巴黎的火车]
[Waiting with my father for the Paris train.]
[那时的荒凉之地，现在更是凄凉的袅无人烟]
[It was desolate then and it'll be more desolate now.]
[我不懂得善待她，对孩子也是如此]
[I treated her so badly. And the children, too.]
[而如今我却再没机会弥补这一切]
[And now I will never be able to make amends.]
[再也不能了]
[Never.]
看着这个
Look at this.
你也能看出来，这不是我们所知的字母表
As you can see, it's not the alphabet we learned at school.
这些字母是按使用频率安排的
These letters are presented in order of usage frequency.
明白吗？
Do you understand?
E，S，A，R，I，N…
E, S, A, R, I, N...
[使用频率？]
[Usage frequency?]
我问过很多同事…
I've talked to a host of colleagues...
…我想我这个方法应该可行
...and I think I've come up with a viable system.
[那恭喜了]
[Good for you.]
方法是这样的
This is how it works.
你想想要说的话，想好之后，就眨眨眼
You think of something to say. When you're ready, blink.
我会朗读这些字母，一个字母一个字母的慢慢读
I'll recite this alphabet, very slowly, letter by letter.
当出现你要表达单词的第一个字母时，你就眨眨眼睛
When I get to the first letter of your word, blink.
我会记下这个字母，之后以此类推
I'll write it down, letter for letter, and so on.
这样，我们就可以组词造句了
In that way we'll form words and sentences.
另外两件事是单词拼好后，眨两下眼睛
Two other things: blink twice when the word is formed.
就好像敲击键盘空格键一样
As if you're hitting the space bar on a keyboard.
要是出错的话，就快速眨眼
And blink rapidly if we make a mistake.
我知道这方法听起来繁琐之极，但是…
I know it sounds terribly arduous but,
相信我，我们很快就会运用自如的
believe me, we'll become expert very quickly.
你的朋友和家人也可以用这个方法和你交流
And your friends and family can use it, too.
准备好了吗？看着我
Are you ready for this? Look at me.
想不想试试看？
Do you want to try?
有什么想说的吗？
Have you thought of something you want to say?
好的
Good.
我们开始吧
So, let's begin.
[等下，不要…]
[Wait, no...]
[我不知道该说些什么]
[I don't know what to say.]
E！
E.
E是你想说的单词首字母吗？
Is E the first letter?
[不是]
[No.]
E不是首字母
E is not the first letter.
[我不知道该说些什么]
[I don't know what to say.]
我知道这并不容易，我们慢慢来
It's difficult, I know, so let's go slowly.
E，S，A…
E, S, A...
[这也太慢了]
[That's too slow.]
[我的眼皮可睁不了那么久，快点！]
[I can't keep my eyelids open that long. Get cracking!]
I！
I...
I吗？
I?
[好]
[Good.]
I是首字母吗？
Is I the first word?
[首字母是I，那就从“我”开始吧]
[My first word is I. I begin with myself.]
E，S…
E, S...
S？
S?
[不是]
[No.]
不是？
No?
不是S
Not S.
[你刚才念的太快了]
[That was too fast.]
[这方法不行，简直太可怕了，根本不可能行得通]
[It doesn't work. This is a nightmare. It'll never work.]
继续好吗？
Shall we go on?
[我受够了]
[I've had enough.]
[别烦我了]
[Leave me alone.]
[上，下，上]
[Up, down, up.]
[我的腋下]
[Under my arms.]
[我的裆部]
[The back of my legs.]
[我已经四十二岁了…]
[I'm forty-two years old...]
[…却象个大婴儿一样被照顾]
[...and I'm being handled like a big baby.]
[我的私处就这样被擦洗包裹]
[my private parts wiped and swaddled.]
[真太荒唐了]
[That's ridiculous.]
[但是正如诗中所云]
[But as the poet says:]
[自我嘲讽，自我娱乐嘛～]
[only a fool laughs when there's nothing to laugh at.]
给我“啵”一个
Blow me a kiss.
快点啊
Come on.
试试
Try it.
加油
Come on.
努力试下
Try.
这不容易
It's difficult.
[别拿镜子]
[No mirror.]
你要努力练习一下
But that's what I want you to work at.
[不要照我的脸]
[Not that face.]
等你休息或是看电视的时候
When you're resting or watching TV, or any time at all,
你要试着练练给我送个香吻
I want you to work at blowing me a kiss.
好吗？
Okay?
[好的]
[Okay.]
另外，你还要尽量多练习的是
And one other thing you have to practise as much as possible.
将舌头滑入上颚后部
And that's sliding your tongue to the back of your palate.
这样你就可以吞咽食物了，看着，就象这样
That's how you'll learn to swallow again. Watch.
[这太不公平了，不公平啊]
[This just isn't fair. Not fair.]
你试一下
You try it.
[快把镜子拿走]
[Put that mirror away.]
张开嘴
Open your mouth.
好的
Good.
试着把舌头往后滑
Try sliding your tongue backwards.
[我做不到]
[I can't.]
试试，继续
Try, go on.
[不行]
[I can't.]
太好了！你的舌头动了
Good! You moved your tongue.
[别骗我了]
[Don't make a fool of me.]
非常好，再来一次
Very good. Again.
简直难以置信，太好了
Unbelievable. Good.
[没错，真难以置信]
[Yes, but true.]
我会帮你练习，直到你可以自己转动头为止，就象这样
I'll help you to move your head on your own. Like that.
[你又来了]
[You're doing it all.]
向左
Left.
好
Good.
向右，好
Right. Good.
再向左
Left again.
能感觉到我的手轻抚你的脸吗？
Can you feel my hands on your face?
[不能]
[No.]
没事的，你会感觉到的，会的
Never mind, you will, you will.
我们对你的遭遇深表同情
We're all very sorry for what's happened to you.
我是《世界时装之苑》的忠实读者，我爱死那杂志了
I'm a regular reader of Elle. I love it.
我只是希望模特不要太男性化
I just wish all the models didn't look like boys.
[我可不这么看]
[I don't think so.]
现在的模特越来越瘦
They're getting thinner and thinner.
令人费解的流行趋势
An odd fashion.
[她可真美]
[How beautiful she is.]
我信念坚强，每天都会为你祈祷的
I have a strong faith. I pray for you every day.
他只有左眼有视力，说话的时候正视他
He can only see with his right eye. Look straight at him when you talk.
[那是谁？]
[Who is that?]
[皮埃尔·罗斯]
[Pierre Roussin.]
还记得我吗？
Do you remember me?
[当然]
[Of course.]
他眨一下眼就是肯定…
He blinks once for yes...
[该死，我没有给他回电话]
[Damn, I didn't call him back.]
- 要我回避下吗？ - 不，不用
- Do you want me to leave?  - No, please not.
[我为什么没给他回电话呢？]
[Why didn't I call him back?]
我听说了你的遭遇，我只是想…
I heard what happened to you. And I just wanted...
因为我的亲身经历，我一定要来看望你
I was compelled to come and see you because of what happened to me.
某种程度上来说，我能理解你现在所经历的
In a way, I know what you're going through
人质的生活和你现在的境地别无二样
Being taken hostage is not so different from what you're going through,
我说的对吗？
Am I right?
[人质？]
[Hostage?]
吉恩-多米尼克善意的将机位让给我
Jean-Dominique was kind enough to give me his seat on a flight
结果那架飞机被劫持作为人质，我在贝鲁特关押了四年
The plane was high-jacked and I remained a hostage in Beirut for four years.
一共是四年，四个月，两周，五天
Four years, four months, two weeks, five days
外加七小时
and seven hours.
他们把我关押在又小又黑的地窖里
They kept me in a cellar. Very small. Dark.
那里简直令人窒息
It was hard to breathe.
我称之为我的坟墓
I called it my tomb.
我对酒颇有研究
I know, a lot about wines.
[他的手是怎么了？]
[What happened to his hand?]
我经常高声背诵一八五五年波尔多葡萄酒分类
I used to recite aloud the wines of the Bordeaux classification of 1855.
玛歌酒，拉菲酒，波亚克酒
Chateau Margaux, Margaux. Chateau Lafite Rotschild, Pauillac.
这些促使我活下来
That's what preserved my sanity.
绝大多数时间，我都极度郁闷，自暴自弃，满腔仇恨
Most times, I was in despair. Suicidal. Angry.
我所遭受的毒打，残暴和污言秽语
The beatings, the filth, the cruelty.
但是最难以忍受的还是那份焦灼的等待
But the worst was the waiting.
可我最终还是活了下来
I survived.
我之所以活下来，是因为坚守自己的尊严
I survived, because I held fast to my own humanity.
那是我仅存的东西，也是我唯一可以做的事情
That's all I could do because that's all I had,
就像此时的你一样
just like you.
坚守尊严，你就能坚强的活下来
Cling to your own humanity and you'll survive.
[尊严？我没听错吧？]
[Humanity? Easy.]
我只是想亲口对你说这些
I just had to say that to you in person.
[为什么他从贝鲁特回来时，我没有给他打电话？]
[Why didn't I call him, when he was back from Beirut?]
[我好过意不去啊]
[I felt too guilty.]
很可笑…
It's ridiculous...
[不，我真是无耻]
[It's not. I feel ashamed.]
I？
I?
W？
W?
我想？
I want?
你想要什么，波比先生？
What do you want, Mr. Bauby?
D！
D.
I！
I.
E！
E.
死
Die.
你想要死？
You want to die?
你怎么敢这么想？
How dare you!
这么多爱你关心你的人
There are people who love you and care for you.
我和你素不相识，却也在这里帮助你
I hardly know you and yet I'm there for you.
你还活着，所以，别说什么“想要死”之类的话
And you're alive. So, don't say you want to die.
这太无礼了
It's offensive and obscene.
还想继续吗？
You want to continue?
好吧
Alright.
我一会再来，看你是不是会改变想法
I'll come back another time and see if you've changed your mind.
对不起
I'm sorry.
[为什么？]
[Why?]
我说的太过了
I went too far.
你好好休息吧
Rest yourself.
喜欢吗？我实在不知道该带什么来看你
Do you like it? I didn't really know what to bring.
看，我还带了这个来
Look, I also brought this.
等一下啊
One moment.
[你这是干什么？]
[What are you doing?]
[那是什么东西？]
[What is that?]
[不要啊，带上会看上去象兔子]
[That's not true. This makes me look like a rabbit.]
我读字母，你眨眼睛，好吗？
I just read the letters and you blink, is that OK?
[随你吧]
[Let it be.]
准备好了？
OK?
S还是A
S of A?
[随你便]
[As you want it.]
[A！]
[A.]
[好，那就A吧]
[Good then A.]
N？
N?
[好，N]
[Good, N.]
[安娜]
[Anne.]
[劳伦，你得看我才成啊]
[You have to look at me, Laurent.]
糟了，我忘了看你了，对不起，我再来一次，这次慢点
Shit, I forgot to look at you. Sorry, I'll start again and slow down.
[随你…]
[As you like it...]
[真有趣]
[Funny.]
我从来都不知道如何探视病人
I've never been a good hospital visitor.
我只会带吃的来，然后自己把它打扫了
I'm the sort who brings food and then eats it.
[不是这样的]
[That's not true.]
为什么这事会发生在你身上？
Why did that have to happen to you?
大家都在谈论你，昨晚，我在甫洛咖啡馆…
Everybody's talking about it. I was in Cafe de Flore last night...
…我听见有人说“你们知道吗，现在吉多成植物人了？”
...I heard someone say, 'Did you know that Jean-Do Bauby is now a complete vegetable?'
[植物人]
[Vegetable.]
他看不到你
He can't see you.
[是谁说的？]
[Who said that?]
[哪种“植物”人？]
[And what sort of vegetable?]
[胡萝卜，土豆还是腌黄瓜？]
[A carrot, a potato, a pickled cucumber?]
[如今看来，我的人生是如此的失败]
[Today it seems to me that my whole life was nothing but a string of failures.]
[那些我无法去爱的女人，那些没有把握住的机会…]
[the women I was unable to love, the chances I failed to seize...]
[…那些不曾珍惜的幸福时光…]
[...the moments of happiness I allowed to drift away...]
[就好像早已能预见到结局的比赛…]
[A race whose result you know beforehand...]
[…但我却偏偏下错赌注]
[...but in which you fail to bet on the winner.]
[我是不是瞎了，或是呆了？]
[Have I been blind or stupid?]
[亦或是只有在残酷现实中，人的本质才得以体现？]
[Or does it take the harsh light of disaster to to show a person their true nature?]
我又回来了
I'm still here.
今天想和我一起努力下吗？
Would you like me to work with you today?
好的
Good.
这个我们会驾轻就熟的
We're going to master this.
同意吗？
Do you agree?
[是的，老大]
[Yes, mistress.]
好的
OK.
那我开始啦
I'll begin.
T？
T?
H？
H?
A？
A?
K？谢谢
K? Thank you.
谢谢？
Thank you?
谢谢
Thank you.
我能叫你吉多吗？
May I call you Jean-Do?
[女人其实很简单]
[Women are not complicated.]
谢谢你，吉多
Thank you, Jean-Do.
I？
I?
我已经？
I have?
[我决定不再自暴自弃]
[I have decided not feel sorry for myself again.]
[除了我的眼睛外，还有两样东西没有瘫痪]
[Apart from my eyes, there two more things that aren't paralysed.]
[我的想象…]
[My imagination...]
[…以及我的记忆]
[...and my memory.]
[只有想象和记忆才能令我摆脱潜水钟的束服]
[My imagination and my memory are the only way I can escape my diving bell.]
[我的想象可以自由驰骋]
[I can imagine anything, anyone, anywhere]
[想象中，马提尼克岛的海水冲刷我的躯体]
[I let the sea wash over me on the isle of Martinique.]
[想象中，我探访深爱着的女人]
[Visit the women I love.]
[想象中，我在万王之王拉姆西斯面前伏首称臣]
[Bow before Ozym Andias, king of kings.]
[我的想象无所不涉]
[I can imagine anything.]
[小时候我就常常幻想着长大]
[As a child I dreamed of my abilities as an adult.]
[如今我却想记住从前的自己]
[Now I want to remember myself as I was.]
[潇洒，快乐，风度翩翩]
[Handsome, debonair, glamorous. And devilishly attractive]
[没错，就是有人夸我潇洒，风度翩翩]
[Yes, glamorous and handsome, some people said.]
[那可不是我，那是马龙·白兰度]
[That's not me, that's Marlon Brando.]
[这才是我]
[That's me.]
- 请问是贝蒂·米兰特吗？ - 对，我就是
- Is this Betty Mialet?  - Yes, this is she.
我是亨瑞特·杜兰德，是贝克海滨医院的医师
My name is Henrite Durand. I'm a therapist at Berck-sur-Mer Naval Hospital.
我是代表我的病人吉恩-多米尼克·波比打电话给你的
I'm calling on behalf of one of my patients, Jean-Dominique Bauby.
吉多？他还好吗？
Jean-Do? How is he?
- 很惬意，但是…  - 我听说他全身瘫痪了
- Comfortable but...  - I heard he's completely paralyzed.
- 不能与外界交流  - 并不完全这样
- That he can't communicate with anybody.  - That's not absolutely accurate.
请进
Come in.
他想请您帮个忙
He wants me to ask you for a favour.
当然了，请稍等一下
Of course. Can you wait a minute?
什么忙都可以
Anything.
他告诉我和您有一本书的合约
He says he has a contract with you for a book.
这是他说的？那就是说他可以说话了，真没想到
He said that? He can speak, I thought he couldn't speak.
他可以的，某种程度上，我一会儿解释给你
He can. In a way. I'll explain later.
- 关于那本书…  - 没错，他是和我们有合约
- About this book...  - Yes, he's got a contract with us,
- …但是，考虑到目前的情况…  - 他想完成合约
- ...but now, given the circumstances...  - He wants to fulfill it.
- 他想写书  - 你不是开玩笑吧？
- He wants to write the book.  - You can't be serious?
我向您保证，他可以的
Let me assure you, he can.
但是您能不能找个人，帮他记录书稿？
but do you think you can find someone to take his dictation?
找个耐心的人
Someone who's patient.
有充裕时间的，特别的人
Somebody with a lot of time. Someone special.
我明白，我回头联系你
Yes, I understand. I'll get back to you.
贝蒂·米兰特说克劳德·曼蒂毕是上天派来的
Betty Mialet said Claude Mendibil was sent from heaven.
说她是最合适的人选
She said no one could be more perfect for this.
贝蒂总是喜欢夸大其辞，我还要和亨瑞特多多练习
Betty always exaggerates. I will have to practise with Henrite.
时刻练习
Any time.
他有话要说
He wants to say something.
不？
No?
别紧张
No panic.
克劳德在医院有个房间，也许你们可以讨论下写书的事情
Claude has taken a room in a hotel. Perhaps you ought to discuss a routine.
[护士每天五点钟叫醒我，我会思考想要写的内容]
[The nurses wake me at 5 a.m. I'll think of what I want to write.]
[你八点过来，之后帮我记录]
[You can come at eight then I'll dictate it to you.]
好的，我会竭尽所能帮你
Good. I'll do my best for you.
[我知道你会的]
[I know you will.]
[我们明天开始，好吗？]
[Can we begin tomorrow?]
没问题
Of course.
透过？
Through?
[透过破旧的窗帘…]
[Through the frayed curtain of my window...]
[…天边的一抹鱼肚白，暗示着崭新的一天]
[...a wan glow announces the break of day.]
[我步履艰难，头昏脑胀]
[My heels hurt, my head weighs a ton]
[我的整个身体像是被囚禁于潜水服中]
[my whole body is encased in a kind of diving suit.]
[我现在的任务就是在这被人遗忘的孤独海岸上…]
[My task now is to write the motionless travel notes...]
[…完成静止的游记]
[...from a castaway on the shores of loneliness.]
[这座海军医院曾经是患肺结核病孩子的收容所]
[This Naval Hospital has in its time been a home to children with tuberculosis]
[大厅里，现在还立着一座白色大理石胸像…]
[In the hall, there's a white marble bust...]
[…那是拿破仑三世的妻子，这座医院的赞助人…]
[...of Empress Eugenie, the wife of Napoleon III...]
[…欧耶尼皇后，她时常来探望这里]
[...the hospital's patroness. She came here regularly.]
[这里曾经有一个减肥中心，一所学校，此外…]
[There was a fat farm, a school and a place where]
[…印象派大师狄亚基雷夫的俄罗斯芭蕾舞团曾在这里排练…]
[...the great Diaghilev rehearsed his Ballet Russe..]
[人们说正是在这里尼金斯基作出了他那惊人的十二英尺腾空跳]
[They say it was here that Nijinsky leapt twelve feet into the air.]
[现在这里没人可以腾空跳]
[No one here now leaps into the air.]
[如今这里都是老弱病残，或者是象我这样失去行动和语言能力的人]
[These days they are all elderly, enfeebled or, like me, rigid and mute.]
[俨然一个残障行营]
[A battalion of cripples.]
[但是我却喜欢被推到一个我称之为“欣欣塔”的地方]
[But I like being wheeled to the place I call Cinecitta.]
[那是一个废弃的大平台]
[A perpetually deserted terrace, a vast series]
[有很多向外延伸的大阳台…]
[of balconies that open onto a landscape...]
[…就象电影场景一样，充满诗意与不规则性]
[...heavy with the poetic and offbeat charm of a movie set.]
[沙丘下的一排排建筑]
[A handful of buildings at the foot of the sand dunes]
[令人想起西方电影中的鬼镇]
[give the illusion of a ghost town in a Western.]
[这幅贝克郊外景致]
[And I enjoy seeing the suburbs of Berck]
[如同火车布景模型般令我陶醉…]
[that look like a model train lay-out..]
[如此白炽的海浪]
[The sea foams such an incandescent white that it might]
[如同特效营造的产物]
[be the product of the special-effects department.]
[但我最欣赏的却是灯塔]
[But my favorite sight of all is the lighthouse.]
[那红白相间的条纹，令人倍感高大，坚固，可靠…]
[tall, robust, reassuring in red and white stripes..]
[我将自己置身于这亲切的标志庇护之下…]
[I place myself under the protection of this brotherly symbol...]
[…它不仅仅是水手的庇护…]
[...guardian not just of sailors but of the sick...]
[…也能将生命垂危之人远离病痛]
[...whom fate has cast to the far edge of life.]
这个小型博物馆的两大亮点就是白色大理石胸像…
The two highlights of this mini museum are a white marble bust...
…刻画的是
...which embodies the radiant youth
…一位神采奕奕的年轻公主…
...of a princess who died with 94...
[五小时的成果，还不赖]
[Five hours of work. Doesn't sound bad.]
[我不是巴尔扎克]
[It's not Balzac.]
还要我继续吗？
Shall I continue?
[给我读读巴尔扎克]
[Read Balzac to me.]
[或者是格雷厄姆·格林（格雷厄姆·格林为英国小说家，剧作家）]
[Or Graham Greene.]
我四十五岁，离异，想和执政官说几句话…
I'm 45 divorced, and I want to speak the consul.
- 那是谁？ - 是男的还是女的？
- What's that?  - Is it a man or a woman?
- 我觉得是男的  - 他在向你眨眼示意呢
- A man. I think.  - He winked at you.
打扰下，是你订的扬声电话吗？
Excuse me, but did you order a speaker phone?
你订了电话吗？
Did you order a phone?
我们走吧
Let's get out of here.
谁叫你们进来的？你们是干什么的？
Who let you in? What are you doing?
我们是法国电信局的
We're from Telecom France.
- 你们应该先去楼下接待处的  - 刚才那儿没人
- You should have gone to Reception first.  - There was no one there.
把电话装在桌子那儿，谢谢
Just install it by the table, please, thank you.
轻点，谢谢
Be careful, please.
我们会通知其他人，你有自己的专用电话
We'll let people know you've got a phone now.
他们打电话来需要提前预约
They'll have to book a time for their calls.
到时候会有人在这里陪你
We'll make sure someone's with you.
对不起，女士，他不能说话吗？
Excuse me, madame, can't he speak?
别以这种目中无人的口气说话
Don't talk about him as if he weren't here.
你问他啊
Ask him.
女士，对不起，要是他不能讲话的话，要电话做什么？
Madame, excuse me, but, if he can't speak what's he want a phone for?
也许他可以喘粗气
Perhaps he's a heavy breather.
你觉得自己很幽默吗？
You think you're funny?
你怎么能这样！
How dare you!
[看来你缺乏幽默感啊，亨瑞特]
[You miss a sense of humor, Henrite.]
三，慢点，四
And three. Calm, four.
[一只黑苍蝇停在我的鼻头上]
[A very black fly settles on my nose.]
[我摇头想赶走它，它却一动不动…]
[I waggle my head to unseat him. He digs in..]
[和这相比，奥运摔跤就是小儿科]
[Olympic wrestling is child's play compared to this.]
你的头动了，你是什么时候会做的？
You moved your head. When did you start doing that?
[谢谢]
[Thank you.]
刚刚？
Just now?
真是奇迹！你现在可以转动头了！
A miracle! You can turn your head!
[玛丽眼里到处都是奇迹]
[Marie sees miracles everywhere.]
莱裴奇医生，他的头动了
Dr. Lepage, he moved his head.
早上好啊
Good morning.
[真是奇迹！他终于知道说早上好了]
[A miracle! He only said good morning once!]
进展，这就是进展
Progress, progress.
[这很好]
[That's better.]
- 他的舌头怎么样？ - 张开嘴
- How's the tongue?  - I'll open your mouth.
舌头动了
The tongue moves
那我们就可以在他的语言功能上再下下功夫了
Then we can go further with his speech.
舌头的运动至关重要，所以你有希望你恢复语言功能
The movement of the tongue is crucial so there's hope.
好，实在是太好了
Great, that's awesome.
我们会努力的，很快你就可以正常吃饭了
We're going to work really hard, soon you'll be able to eat normally.
[文字只有在阅读时才是真实存在的]
[A text is only real when it's read.]
[我出事之前帮我爸爸刮了胡子]
[I shaved my father when I visited him the last time before my accident.]
[他身体不适，所以我整夜留在他巴黎的公寓里陪他]
[He was unwell and I stayed overnight in his apartment in Paris.]
[转天早上，我帮他刮了胡子]
[The next morning I shaved his stubble.]
- 我刮胡子给谁看呢？ - 给我
- Who can see if I'm shaven?  - Me.
- 我好怕  - 怕什么？
- I'm terrified.  - Of what?
你给我刮胡子
You shaving me.
- 你总是笨手笨脚的  - 这是从你那遗传的
- You were always so damned clumsy.  - That runs in the family.
没错
Sure.
- 要咖啡吗？ - 不要
- Coffee?  - No.
- 别折腾他了，他不舒服  - 刮胡子怎么算是折腾？
- Don't tire him. He's not well.  - How can a shave tire him?
- 你妈妈更漂亮些  - 没错
- Your mother was prettier.  - That wouldn't be difficult.
- 你还记得你妈妈吗？ - 当然了
- Do you remember your mother?  - Oh yeah.
你总问我这个问题，我以前总是回答“记不清了”
You always ask me that and I always say the same thing: not really.
你现在在读什么书？
What are you reading at the moment?
基督山伯爵
Reading. The Count of Monte Cristo.
为什么？
Why?
因为我想写个现代版的
Because I'm thinking of writing a modern version.
- 现代版的基督山伯爵？ - 是啊
- Of the Count of Monte Cristo?  - Yes.
当然复仇还会是作品的主线…
Vengeance will still be the driving force...
…但我会把场景设在当今，而且基督山伯爵会是个女人
...but I'm setting it in today's world. And Monte Cristo will be a woman.
- 基督山女伯爵？ - 对，就是个女人
- The Countess of Monte Cristo..?  - Yes, a woman.
- 那我是不会读的  - 书我还没开始写呢
- I don't want to read it.  - I haven't written it yet.
但是我已经和出版商签了合约
But I've got a contract with a book publisher.
你要是把我刮伤了，我可要告你
If you cut me, I'll sue.
- 医生昨天来过了  - 说了什么？
- The doctor came yesterday.  - And?
- 他说我能活到一百岁  - 好啊，我一定给你好好庆祝一下
- He says I'll live to be a hundred.  - Good. I'll give you a great party.
我是不会出席的，又有谁想活到一百岁呢？
I won't attend. Who wants to live to be a hundred?
吉多，谁都别告诉
Jean-Do, don't tell a soul.
我还想念着你妈妈
I still miss your mother.
我不会告诉别人的，这是我们之间的秘密
I won't. It's our secret.
- 你应该和席琳结婚的  - 会有什么区别吗？
- You should have married Cine.  - What difference would that have made?
那样你就不会轻易离开她，也不会离开你的孩子们
You wouldn't have left her so easily. And your children.
- 我们非要谈这个吗？ - 我知道自己在说什么
- Do we have to talk about this?  - I know what I'm talking about.
没人比我的情史丰富，当然，也许只有卡萨诺瓦一个人吧
No one had more affairs than I did. Well, maybe Casanova, but no one else.
和别的女人有染
Having an affair with another woman is no reason
并不能成为你离开孩子母亲的原因
for leaving the mother of your children.
现在再也没有什么道德标准了，这一点都不可笑，是事实
There are no standards anymore. It's not funny, it's true.
带孩子们来看我，席琳会带他们来
And bring your children to see me. Sylvie brings them, too.
- 你也该这么做  - 好的，只是我一直没有时间
- You should bring them as well.  - OK, I haven't found time yet.
- 来  - 那是什么？
- Here.  - What is that?
- 橙花水  - 我可不想闻起来象妓女
- Orange blossom.  - Do I have to smell like a tart?
这可是春药的味道
It's an aphrodisiac.
好，那姑娘们就会闻风而逃
Good. That'll make the girls come running.
没错，但是他们还是会闻到你身上的味道
Sure, but give them a chance to smell you.
让我来照照镜子
Let me look at myself.
还不错嘛，这看起来都不像我了
Not bad. My God, they don't make them like me anymore.
我本来有话要告诉你的
I wanted to tell you something.
- 不过我不记得了  - 会想起来的
- Can't remember.  - It'll come back.
我可不这么想
I'm not so sure.
- 遗忘的东西越来越多  - 别夸大
- I remember less and less.  - Don't exaggerate.
哦，我想起来了
Oh yes, I remember.
我以你为荣，真的
I'm very proud of you. I really am.
还有些别的…
And something else...
实在记不得了
Can't remember.
[父亲的赞同，那时令我欣慰…]
[A father's approval. I found it comforting then...]
[…现在觉得更加令人欢心鼓舞]
[...and I find it even more comforting now. We are all children.]
[我们都是孩子，我们都需要别人的肯定]
[We all need approval.]
[我想见见我的孩子]
[I want to see my children.]
我们来了，今天是父亲节
Here we are. Father's Day.
父亲节快乐
Happy Father's Day!
[我想即使是一张草图，一个阴影，一些碎片，都是磨灭不了的父亲形象]
[I guess that even a rough sketch, a shadow, a tiny fragment of a dad is still a dad.]
[父亲节这天，儿子为我擦拭掉唇边流下的口水]
[Father's Day. My son wiping the saliva that escapes my closed lips.]
[之前我们从未共同庆祝过这种节日]
[We have never before fitted this made-up holiday into our emotional calendar.]
克劳德说书进展很顺利，我简直不敢相信你在写作
Claude says the book's going well. I can't believe you're writing it.
我始终认为你是我所认识最不可思议的男人
I still think you're the most surprising man I've ever known.
来看望你的人多吗？
Have you had lots of visitors?
劳伦，安娜-玛丽…
Laurent, Anne-Marie...
…米歇尔…
...Michel...
就这些？她没有来？
That's it? She hasn't?
我还以为她疯狂的爱着你呢
I thought she was supposed to be madly in love with you.
算了，那是她的事
Well, that's her business.
我们来练习一下字母表好吗？
Shall we practice that alphabet?
我中风前一周开始节食
When I began a diet a week before my stroke
…从没想过会有这么显著的成果
...I never dreamed of such dramatic results.
现在他们知道有个丑八怪爸爸是什么感觉了，谢谢
Now they know what it's like to have a zombie for a father. Thank you.
这可一点都不好笑
That's not amusing.
孩子们
Kids.
想不想玩猜词游戏，爸爸？
You want to play Hangman, dad?
我来帮你，小声说个字
I'll help you. Whisper a word.
第一个字母是C，最后一个字母是E，整个单词一共七个字母
The first letter is a C, the last an E. The word has 7 letters.
就这些
That's it.
来和爸爸道别，我们该走了
Say goodbye to your dad, kids. We're leaving.
再见，爸爸
Bye, dad.
再见，爸爸，下周见
Bye dad. See you next week.
[我的自责难以言表]
[It's hard to describe my grief.]
[我是他们的父亲，却不能触摸他们，无法轻抚他们的头发…]
[I'm their father, but I can't touch them, run my fingers through their hair...]
[…无法紧紧的拥抱他们]
[...and hug them tight.]
[但是我喜欢静静的看他们玩耍和嘻笑]
[But I like to see them play and laugh.]
[这就是我对美好一天的定义]
[That's what I call a wonderful day..]
[我有些自怨自艾，是不是？]
[I feel sorry for myself, don't you think?]
你以前真的很幸福
You were genuinely happy.
[你真这么想？]
[You think so?]
[也许吧]
[Perhaps.]
[我不想错过这比赛，一边去！]
[I don't want to miss this. Step aside!]
好好享用，再见
Enjoy. See you.
[再见，你在干什么？]
[Yeah, see you. What are you doing?]
[我想要视觉大餐，或是我该出去饱餐一顿？]
[I want TV-meals. Or shall I go out for dinner?]
[我应该去拉杜克好好享受一下]
[I will treat myself to a feast at Le Duc.]
- 在这里遇到你真巧  - 这不是很美妙吗？
- What a coincidence to find you here.  - Isn't that amazing?
吃牡蛎吗？
An oyster?
一切都如同梦境般美好
It seems like it was just yesterday when I first heard your name.
甜美
Sweet.
别恭维我
No compliments.
开始下一章吗？
And the next chapter?
[周日，我惧怕周日]
[Sunday. I dread Sunday.]
[他们打开电视]
[When they turn the TV on,]
[是绝好的一招]
[they have to make sure they're doing it right.]
[及其具有战略性]
[That is very strategic.]
[通常几个小时才会有人来瞅你一眼]
[It can take hours until the next good Samaritan comes by.]
[周日，太可怕了，没有语言医师，没有精神医师]
[Horrible, these Sundays. No speech therapists, no psychotherapist.]
[没有理疗师，没有访客，只有空旷的医院]
[No physiotherapist, no visitors. A skeleton staff.]
[周日就是荒凉的代名词]
[Sunday is a long stretch of desert.]
[但是今天，玛丽善意的提出要带我去做弥撒]
[But today, Marie nobly suggests she takes me to mass.]
[我试图解释自己并不是什么信徒，不过无济于事]
[I have tried to explain to her that I am not a religious man, but without avail.]
[全世界都在为我祈祷]
[All over the world people are praying for me.]
[最虔诚的就是我女儿席莱斯特]
[Top of the list is my daughter, Cileicester]
[当然还有玛丽]
[And Marie, of course.]
[众神都被召集，来帮助我]
[The most diverse deities have been enlisted to help me.]
[在尼泊尔，听说人们在为我颂歌]
[In Nepal, I'm told, they chant a mantra for me.]
[在喀麦隆，人们在为我祈求非洲之神的祝福]
[In Cameroon holy man has procured for me the goodwill of Africa's gods.]
[我已经为他献上了我的右眼]
[I have assigned him my right eye.]
[我承认自己试图依赖这神圣的精神力量…]
[I can't deny that I have attempted to organise this vast spiritual energy...]
[…作为活下去的动力]
[...to support my existence.]
[这也许不足为题，也许是自欺欺人，但是我会竭尽所能，奋力一搏]
[It may not be admirable, it may even be a touch hypocritical, but I'll try anything.]
很高兴在这里见到你
I'm very pleased to see you here.
几天前我探望过你
I came to visit you a few days ago. I brought
给你带了圣餐
the Blessed Sacrament to give you Communion.
但是当时你在睡觉
But you were asleep.
- 对，他是睡着了  - 什么？
- Yes, he was asleep.  - What?
你现在想接受圣餐礼吗？
Would you like me to give you Holy Communion now?
不
No.
是的
Yes.
想叫我为你祝福吗？
Would you like me to say a blessing over you?
- 不要  - 好的
- No.  - Yes.
神圣的主啊，请施恩于吉恩-多米尼克
Heavenly Father, have mercy on Jean-Dominique,
他正遭受折磨
who is cruelly afflicted.
请治愈他的肉体，令他卸下精神上的负担
Help his body to heal, keep his spirits buoyant,
[- …帮助他获得信念  - 我精神上没负担啊，神父]
[- ...and help him to find faith.  - My spirit is very buoyant, mister.]
[- 以神父，圣子…  - 你耍我啊]
[- In the name of the father...  - You made a fool of me.]
神？
Fa?
神父？
Father?
以前…
There are...
[神父，波尔多的修道士经常为我祈祷]
[Father, there are monks in Bordeaux who regularly dedicate their prayers to me.]
…经常为我祈祷
...who regularly dedicate their prayers to me.
- 是吗？那太好了  - 但是其效果甚微
- Do they, that's good.  - But the results have been unremarkable.
我们一定要耐心
We must be patient.
[对，医生们也这么说]
[Yes, the doctors say that, too.]
吉恩-多米尼克，我想提个建议
But Jean-Dominque, I want to suggest something to you
几周后，我会引领卢尔德朝圣
In a few weeks time, I shall be leading a pilgrimage to Lourdes.
[卢尔德？]
[Lourdes?]
比特丽思和我觉得你可能也愿意加入
Dear Beatrice and I thought you might want to be part of it.
[这是个圈套]
[This is a trap.]
已经有些病人在那里神奇的康复了
There have been some miraculous cures.
没错
That's true.
[我去过卢尔德]
[I've been to Lourdes.]
- 就到这里，我们往回开吧  - 我不走回头路的
- Let's stop and return.  - I am not turning back.
这是我的车，我想开到哪都行
Hit's my car, I'll drive where I like.
- 你说了想过个疯狂的周末  - 我可没这么说过
- You said you wanted a dirty weekend.  - I never said that.
你说过
Yes you did.
卢尔德可不是过疯狂周末的地方
Lourdes is not the right place for a dirty week-end.
你怎么一根筋啊！
You've got a one-track mind.
我想去看圣母玛利亚
I want to see the Madonna.
- 我才不相信那些东西  - 我想去看看，并且尝尝圣水
- I don't believe in any of this.  - I want to see her and drink holy water.
饶了我吧
Spare me this.
你也该这么做，这对你有好处
You should do that too. It will be good for you.
很壮观，是不是？
Imposing, hm?
我去买盛圣水的瓶子
I'll buy some bottles for the holy water.
- 我受不了了，我要走了  - 别，这对你有好处
- That's it for me. I'm leaving.  - Stay. It could do you a lot of good.
别那么肯定，说不定会很危险
Don't be so sure, it might be dangerous.
要是圣母玛利亚显灵的时候
What if someone in perfect health happened to be here when
这正好站着个身强力壮的人怎么办？
the Madonna appeared?
奇迹显现，他瘫患了
One miracle, and he'd end up paralyzed.
你这人太不虔诚了
You are terrible.
- 你好  - 你好，女士
- Hello.  - Good day, madam.
看！那是属于我的圣母！
Look! Here's my Madonna!
- 别瞎想了  - 好，那你以后少搭理我
- Forget it.  - Yeah, get out of my life.
好吧，这个我送你
Okay, I'll give it to you as a present
圣母有天眼，这尊像是红衣大主教开过光的
Madame has a wonderful eye. This Madonna been blessed by the Cardinal.
- 我们还有三一八吗？ - 到储藏室找找看
- Do we have more 318's?  - Look in the storage.
- 多少钱？ - 一千八百九十九法郎
- How much is that?  - 1899 franc.
- 我们认识吗？ - 我可不这么想，先生
- Don't we know each other?  - I don't think so, Mister.
我没有零钱
I don't have change.
她这么一直盯着，我怎么和你做爱？
I can't make love to you with her looking at me.
我明白
I understand.
我这可不是在陈述事实，我这是在抱怨
I wasn't stating a fact, I was making a complaint.
我去把她关上
Let me turn her off
不
No.
这是世上唯一一个被红衣大主教开过光的圣母
The only one in the whole world. Blessed by the Cardinal.
约瑟芬，回了巴黎我们就得分手
Josephine, when we get back to Paris we're going to have to split up.
- 因为她吗？ - 不，因为我们之间的一切
- Because of her?  - No. Because of everything.
好吧，你说的没错
OK, you're right.
- 我要再出去一下  - 把灯关上
- I'll go out again.  - Turn off the lights.
别关我的圣母
But not my Madonna.
加油，吉多
Come on, Jean-Do.
要是你学会发“L”的音，就可以吞咽食物了
If you learn the L sound you'll learn to swallow.
你就能开口说卢尔德了
And you'll learn to say Lourdes.
这样可以吗？舒服吗？
Is that okay? Is it comfortable?
[《高压锅》这个题目可以作为我正在描写的…]
['The Pressure Cooker' could be the title of the piece...]
[…这里所经历的一切]
[...I'm writing about my experiences here.]
[也可以起名叫《眼睛》或者是《潜水钟》]
[I could also call it 'The Eye' or 'The Diving Bell'.]
[地点和情节大家想必已经了解]
[Plot and location are well known.]
[在病房中，正值壮年的L先生…]
[In a hospital room, there's Mr. L, at the climax of his life...]
[…在经历了一次严重中风之后，正与闭锁性综合症相依为命]
[...trying to live with locked-in syndrome after a serious stroke.]
[雄心勃勃又稍稍有些愤世嫉俗的L先生…]
[Ambitious and somewhat cynical, because he didn't know failures before...]
[…在遭遇此次不幸之前，还未曾品味过失败的痛苦]
[...becomes acquainted with misfortune.]
[当你们还在缓缓聆听…]
[We his slow transformation listening to a commentarial voice...]
[…L先生这些内心独白的话外音时]
[...which tells the inner monologue of Mr. L.]
[我已经想好了最后一幕，那是在夜晚]
[I already have the last scene. It's night.]
[这位自打本书开始就遭受瘫痪折磨的L先生…]
[Mr. L, who was paralysed since the beginning of the piece...]
[…突然间从床上蹦起来，跑上灯光昏暗的舞台]
[...suddenly jumps out of his bed and runs over the darkly lit stage.]
[之后光线又暗下来，此时响起了L先生的话外音]
[Then it gets dark again and we hear Mr. L's commentarial voice:]
[tmd，原来是个梦]
[Fuck, it was a dream.]
起来，你能站起来
Stand up. I can stand up.
一切都会好起来
Everything is alright.
我想知道这一切是怎么发生的
'I want to remember how all this happened to me.'
要不要问问什么人？
Shall I ask someone?
不要？
No?
- 你好，这里是一一九房间  - 你是谁？
- Hello, room 119.  - Who's that?
我是克劳德·曼蒂毕，吉多在我身边
I'm Claude Mendibil. I'm sitting with Jean-Do.
[我是他父亲]
[This is his father speaking.]
我们正等您的电话呢
Yes, we were expecting your call.
我该怎么做？就是聊天吗？
So what do I do? Just talk?
[吉多可以听到你，他会回答你的]
[Jean-Do can hear you. He will answer you.]
[你可以听到我说字母表…]
[You'll hear me saying the alphabet and...]
我知道，席琳告诉过我
Yes, Cine told me.
[说吧，波比先生]
[Just talk, Monsieur Bauby.]
他能听到我吗？
Can he hear me?
吉恩-多米尼克，我是老豆
Jean-Dominique? This is Papinou.
[我现在坐在窗前]
[I'm sitting at the open window.]
[你好吗？是不是这个问题太傻了？]
[How are you or is that a fool question?]
对，是很傻
Yes, it's a fool question.
我好想你
I miss you.
[我也想你]
[I miss you, too.]
天啊！这样根本就不可能交谈
God Almighty! This is an impossible way to conduct a conversation.
我想说什么都不记得了，不，不，我想起来了
Everything goes out of my mind. No, no, I've remembered.
[我给你寄了个礼物，是给你的意外惊喜]
[I'm sending you a present. It's a surprise.]
[我想啊…]
[I had a thought...]
…我们，我们现在的处境相同
...about us. We're in the same boat.
我被困在这公寓，不能起来，不能上下楼
I'm stuck in this apartment. I can't get up and down the stairs.
[不信的话，等你九十二岁的时候下四层楼梯试试]
[You try four flights of stairs when you're ninety-two years old.]
[我们都被困囚笼]
[we're both locked-in cases.]
[你被身体所困，而我则被这栋公寓所困]
[You in your body and me in my apartment.]
吉多，记住…
Jean-Dominique, remember,...
…我写字台右手边第一个抽屉里有封信…
...in the top right-hand drawer of my writing desk there's a letter..
里面是我的遗嘱…
In it are my last wishes. It's in a file...
…夹在标着“杂七杂八”标记的文件夹里
...marked 'Miscellaneous'.
[好了，不说了]
[I must stop now.]
- 别哭  - 可我就是控制不住
- Don't cry.  - That's easy to say.
你可是我的儿子啊
You're my son for Christ's sake.
再见，吉多
Good-bye, Jean-Dominique.
我差点忘了，你生日快到了
I forgot, it's almost your birthday.
[我会再打给你的]
[I'll call again.]
[生日快乐]
[Happy Birthday.]
[知道听不到儿子的答复，这对一个父亲来说心如刀割]
[It can't be easy for a father to speak to a son who he knows will never reply.]
我觉得外出观景对你有好处
I thought an outing with a new vista would do you good.
还有个惊喜给你，闭上眼睛
I have another surprise for you. Close your eyes.
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
好了，现在睁开
Okay, now open them.
基督山伯爵
THE COUNT OF MONTE CRISTO
[没必要这么破费，居然是两卷册的]
[That was not necessary. In two volumes.]
这并不是第一版，但是也很有年头了
It's not a first edition, but it's pretty old.
想不想叫我给你读一段？哪一章呢？
Would you like me to read something to you? Which chapter?
[我们应该用罗马数字，居然没有想到用罗马数字]
[We should use Roman digits. We didn't think of Roman digits.]
[罗马数字是怎么编号的？]
[What would it be in Roman digits?]
[L，I，X]
[That's L, I, X.]
[那样就快多了，下次用罗马数字吧]
[That's faster. Next time.]
[- 五十？再往后？ - 对，再往后]
[- 50? Higher?  - Yes, higher.]
九？五十九？好的
Nine? 59? OK.
好的，找到了
OK, there we go.
[里面居然有插画，我被这个巧合震惊了]
[There's even an illustration. The coincidence frightens me.]
他们在他旁边坐下
'They sat down beside him.'
[诺瓦迪埃坐在被整日安置的轮椅上…]
['Noirtier was sitting in a wheelchair where they put him from morning till evening...]
[…面前的镜子令他不费吹灰之力…]
[...in front of a mirror which allowed him to see the whole apartment...]
[就看清整栋公寓]
[without attempting any movement:]
这些如今对他来说已成为奢望
this was something that had become impossible for him.
视力和听觉是仅存的感官…
Sight and hearing were the only two senses...
…象两束火苗，依然在他胸膛燃烧
...which, like two sparks, still lit up this human matter.'
…在他胸膛燃烧
'... this human matter.'
[那就是我，你觉得呢？]
[That's me, don't you think?]
[- 不  - 是的]
[- But no.  - But yes.]
[人们被我吓跑，我令他们颤抖]
[I frighten people, make them shudder.]
不是的
You don't.
[我不应该碰大仲马的作品]
[I should have stayed away from Dumas.]
[不应该篡改名著，这就是教训]
[Don't tamper with a masterpiece. That's the lesson.]
[我并不知道自己会成为诺瓦迪埃这样的人]
[I didn't know Noirtier was the man I was going to become.]
[我的潜水钟将你同我一起拖至海底]
[My diving bell has dragged you down to the bottom of the sea with me..]
吉多，我并不介意你将我拖至海底…
Jean-Do, I don't find it so bad that you drag me down to the bottom of the sea...
…因为你同时也是我的多彩蝴蝶
...because you are also my butterfly.
[这是爱的宣言]
[That's a declaration of love.]
[等我们完成这本书…]
[After we finish this book...]
[…我们再继续合作下一本关于长跑运动员的书]
[...we'll write another one about a long-distance runner.]
[也许有朝一日，我会成为他那样的人…]
[You never know. Perhaps I'll become like him...]
斗牛比赛你没能来
'I missed you at the bullfight.
希望明年能见，吉恩-保罗
I hope we meet again next year. Jean-Paul.'
写于探戈，尼姆
Le Tango, Nimes.
亲爱的波比先生，您定制的汽车…
'Dear Mr. Bauby, the customized campmobile...
…会在收到定单后的六至八周发出
...can be delivered six to eight weeks after your order.
亨利·雷纳德，这可是个好消息
Yours sincerely, Henri Raynaud.' That's good news.
这是老豆寄来的
This is from Papinou.
是个礼物
'This is a present.'
看，你孩童时的照片
Look, a photo of you as a kid.
吉多，八岁，摄于贝克海滨
Jean-Do, aged eight, Berck sur Mer.
这是安娜·玛丽寄来的
From Anne-Marie.
- 吉恩-多米尼克病房  - 你是哪位？
- Jean-Dominique Bauby's room.  - Who are you?
席琳·戴斯毛利斯，你是哪位？
Cine Desmoulins. And you?
[我是伊莱斯，我想和吉多说几句话]
[Elese. I want to speak with Jean-Do.]
等一下
One moment.
我把扬声器打开，这样他就可以听到你了
I turned the speaker on, so he can hear you.
[你在那，我没法说]
[I can't speak with you there.]
只能这样，这里没有别人了
You have to, there's no one else.
[医师也不在吗？]
[Isn't the therapist there?]
不，她今天不在
No, she's not here today.
[亲爱的？]
[Darling?]
[我知道答应过去看你，可到了车站，我还是忍不住掉头回来]
[I know I said I'd come but I got as far as the train station and then turned back.]
[我实在是做不到]
[I just can't.]
[请原谅我]
[Please forgive me.]
[席琳？]
[Cine?]
什么事？
Yes.
[你能不能出去一下？有些事我要单独和吉多讲]
[Can't you just go out for a moment? I have personal things to say.]
[你在场我讲不出来]
[I feel embarrassed.]
我不能留下他一个
I can't leave him.
这里没有别人了，等下，他有话要说
There's nobody else. Wait, he wants to say something.
O？
O?
一？
One?
一分钟？
One minute?
我出去了，但是一会儿就回来
I'm leaving. But not for long.
[吉多，你现在是一个人吗？]
[Jean-Do, are you alone now?]
[亲爱的…]
[Darling...]
[我爱你胜于一切]
[I love you more than ever.]
[我想来看望你，不过我始终没有勇气]
[I want to see you but I haven't the courage.]
[我想在脑海中保留从前的你]
[I want to think of you as you were.]
[希望你早日康复]
[I hope you'll recover.]
[我好想你]
[I miss you.]
[我想念你，感觉好孤独]
[I miss you and I feel so alone.]
[我知道你能明白]
[I know you understand.]
[我无时无刻不在想着你]
[You're in my thoughts all the time.]
[我知道你的家人时刻和你在一起]
[I know your family is always with you.]
[你想叫我来看望吗？]
[Do you want me to come?]
我回来了
I'm back.
[你想叫我来看望吗？]
[Do you want me to come?]
我回来了，伊莱斯
I'm back, Elese.
每…
Every...
每时每刻
Every day.
每时每刻我…
Every day I'm...
每时每刻我都在等你
Every day I'm waiting for you.
[我听不清，能再重复一下吗？]
[I can't understand you. Could you repeat that?]
[我听不清]
[I can't understand you.]
他说：我每时每刻都在等你
He said: I'm waiting for you every day.
要是不搭乘这趟航班，我就赶不上去香港了
If I don't get a seat on this plane, I will miss my connection to Hong-Kong.
那我的位子让给你好了
Take mine.
- 我坐下班飞机  - 谢谢
- I'll take the next flight.  - Thank you.
旅途愉快
Have a good trip.
但是你这可不是去香港啊，你会去贝鲁特
But you're not going to Hong Kong you are going to Beirut.
怎么了？不舒服吗？
Anything wrong? You don't feel good?
没事的
Don't worry.
[大多数时候，我都会忘记梦境]
[Most times I forget my dreams.]
[给你说梦的人都极其无聊]
[People who tell you their dreams are tiresome.]
[但是这个梦却不断的出现，我还搞不清究竟为何]
[But this one comes again and again. I don't know why.]
[我好害怕]
[I'm afraid.]
[这种厄运的感觉挥之不去]
[The feeling of doom wouldn't leave.]
[只有被称之为“奇迹”的东西，才能拯救我的灵魂]
[It took what I can only describe as a miracle to lift my spirits.]
[崇尚个人奇迹是危险的]
[It's dangerous to believe in personal miracles.]
[这让人妄自尊大]
[They tend to make one feel self-important.]
[但是，我得承认，奇迹确实发生了]
[Nevertheless, I must report that I believe something miraculous did occur]
[我开始能唱歌了]
[I began to sing.]
[我咕哝，我唱歌]
[I grunt, I sing.]
[我的听力不大灵光，有时候我却可以听到自己的心跳]
[My hearing isn't great and sometimes I think I hear my heart beating.]
[但是我告诉自己，那是蝴蝶扇动羽翼的声音]
[But I tell myself it's the sound of butterfly's wings.]
[是的，我们不屈不挠的前进着，我甚至有可能拥有蝴蝶的听觉]
[Yes, I am making indomitable progress and I may even have butterfly hearing.]
[我也可以展望未来，夏天即将结束…]
[I can look forward to the future. Soon the summer will come to an end...]
[…我将要开始在医院的第一个秋季生活]
[...and I will begin my first autumn in this hospital.]
[这里就是我的生活]
[My life is here.]
[周而复始的循环]
[An everlasting repetition.]
[就在这里]
[Here.]
你好吗？
How goes it?
他说话了
He's speaking!
- 你在说话  - 他还会唱歌呢
- You're speaking.  - He can sing a song, too.
- 来，给劳伦唱一个  - 快点，给我唱一个
- Come on, sing for Laurent.  - Please, for me.
你还好吗？
Are you OK?
- 他是在唱歌吗？ - 不，不是
- Does he sing?  - No, he doesn't.
[我得了肺炎]
[I have pneumonia.]
[就在我刚刚幻想…]
[Just when I thought...]
[就好像水手注视着渐渐消逝的海岸一样]
[Like a sailor who watches the shore gradually disappear.]
[我注视着过去的自己一点点消失]
[I watch my past recede.]
[逐渐被遗忘]
[Becoming ashes of oblivion.]
[我这真是衣锦还乡啊…]
[What a comeback.]
[那里是我工作的地方]
[That's where I worked.]
[那对夫妇，我认识，但是却不记得他们的名字]
[And that couple, I know them, but I can't remember their names.]
[那是我的车！]
[That's my car!]
[我的新车]
[My new car.]
喇叭在哪里？
Where is the horn?
- 让我抱一下  - 看到我的新车了吗？
- Let me hug you.  - See my car?
太酷了！
Lovely.
一切都还好吗，西奥？
Everything OK, Theo?
这周过的还不错吧
Had a good week?
- 我们要去看戏吗？ - 看戏？只要你想去
- Are we going to a theatre?  - To a theatre? If you want to.
- 能吃牡蛎吗？ - 你现在喜欢牡蛎了？
- Can we have oysters?  - Do you like oysters now?
别太晚送他回来
Don't bring him back too late.
我们走了
We are leaving.
- 我能坐前排吗？ - 当然了，后面也没座啊
- Can I get in the front?  - Sure, there's no room in the back.
过一段我也带你出去玩
Soon I will take you too.
是不是感觉有风吹？
A little bit of wind?
- 你们球队还好吗？ - 嗯，队员们都还不错
- Your team OK?  - Yeah, the players are OK.
- 训练之后你们冲澡吗？ - 冲，还洗衣服什么的
- You take a shower afterwards?  - We shower and wash our stuff.
- 你的蛋蛋长头发了吗？ - 还没
- Got pubic hair around your willy?  - No, not yet.
我们队里以前有个家伙不肯脱衣服冲澡
We had one guy who didn't want to undress for the shower.
俱乐部就强迫他，还打了一架
The club said he had to. There was a fight.
可他还是不肯，后来她妈来劝他
He didn't do it. His mother appeased him.
最后，他就离开球队了
In the end, he had to leave the team.
你们没有这样的问题？
You don't have that problem, do you?
- 还有什么新闻？妈妈还好吗？ - 挺好的
- Other news? Everything OK with mom?  - Yeah, she's OK.
- 你认识这条路吗？ - 认识，去黛安娜阿姨家就从这走
- You know this way?  - Yes, it's the way to Aunt Diane.
很热，是不是？
It's hot. You feel that, too?
我没觉得啊
No, I don't.
我们…
We have...
可能要下雨了，我要停一下车
It might start to rain. I'll stop for a moment.
爸，怎么了？
Dad, what's the matter?
给你妈妈打电话！
Phone your mother!
我最后想的是我们要取消看戏的计划
My last thought was we'll have to cancel going to the theatre.
肯定晚了，不过我们明晚会去
We'd be late in any case. We'll go tomorrow night.
之后我就陷入了无尽的昏迷
And then I sank into a coma.
是本书吗？
Is it a book?
献给西奥菲勒，席莱斯特和霍顿斯
For Theophile, Cileicester and Hortense.
我希望他们的生活充满多彩的蝴蝶
I wish them lots of butterflies.
衷心的感谢克劳德·曼蒂毕
And my deepest gratitude to Claude Mendibil.
没有她，就不会有这本书的出版
You'll understand that without her this book couldn't have been written.
我一直在你身边
I was here the whole time.
你知道的
You know that.
这些评论棒极了！想不想听听？
These reviews are terrific! You want to hear them?
作者在寂静中口述，没有手势，没有言语
The man who dictates in silence. Without gestures or speech.
吉恩-多米尼克·波比用眼皮进行交流，创作本书
Jean-Dominque Bauby communicates with an eyelid and writes this book.
这是对遭难的一次心灵访问
A touching visit at the wreckage of abandonment.
厄纳·查皮斯 评
By Bernard Chapuis.
感人至深
'A touching book.'
吉恩-多米尼克·波比，四十三岁，杰出记者
Jean-Dominique Bauby, 43 years old, respected journalist,
慈爱父亲，开拓先锋…
father, free man...
…曾计划撰写有关女性复仇小说
...planned to write a novel about revenge for women
吉恩-多米尼克·波比，于1997年3月9日…
Jean-Dominique Bauby died on March 9, 1997...
…在其作品《潜水钟与蝴蝶》出版十天后去世
...10 days after the publication of 'The Diving Bell and the Butterfly'.
感谢观赏
TLF中文字幕站
http://tlfsubs.eastgame.net
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者